Thank you.
Good morning, everybody.
Go on in the auditorium if you're out in the lobby.
I appreciate you guys getting up early on a Saturday and coming in.
I fully expect, I don't know.
Thank you, I'm very happy to say, I'm very happy to hear you, I'm very happy to say there's
22 churches represented today.
They're probably not all here yet, but hopefully it'll be, you know, help us really, what's
sometimes a difficult conversation between churches about a book that has a lot of different, people
have a lot of different strong views about.
And so, you know, we're going to have a lot of things that are going to have a lot of things that are going to have a lot of things that are going to be able to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things.
So if you have a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to be doing with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things that are going to do with a lot of things.
Father God, thank you for bringing everybody together.
I pray for those that are still on the road.
I pray for those that are in Venezuela and in the Middle East and are going through all the crises in which we'd love to see your hand displayed.
And I pray that each of us, as we try to map the Bible to the world around us and see in Revelation how we deal with tribulation and wars and rumors of wars,
I just pray that you would give us your insight.
And let us see you in the midst of it.
Focus on you in the boat with us, not the storm around us.
Thank you for this day and our power to help us to focus and hear you more clearly.
In Jesus' name, amen.
All right, so, my official introduction.
We are delighted to welcome Mr. David DeSilva, Dr. David DeSilva.
He is the Trustee's Distinguished Professor of New Testament and Greek at Aslan Theological Seminary,
an ordained elder with the Global Methodist Church,
the author of over 40 books,
primarily regarding New Testament texts and culture,
many of which are on sale in the lobby.
He's worked on major Bible translation projects for the Common English Bible and English Standard Version,
created video resources and mobile ed courses for faith life.
His book, An Introduction to the New Testament,
has been nurturing Christians in English, Arabic, Chinese, and Korean.
Dr. DeSilva and his wife, Donna G, live in Port Charlotte, Florida,
where he also serves as an organist, choir director,
and choir director at Port Charlotte Global Methodist Church,
and we're immensely proud and privileged to have you here with us today.
We really are.
Thank you very much.
Please welcome Dr. DeSilva.
Thank you, Ken.
Thank you very much.
Thank you to everyone at Canvas that has made this such a nice welcome,
starting with a lovely dinner last night.
I had a chance to meet the staff and some members of the board.
Thanks for being here and looking into this challenging book with me.
The approach that I am, I'll just put it this way, I'm from New Jersey, right?
So, the approach that I'm trying to sell is somewhat different from that which is most popularly known out there.
And if you take nothing away beside this, take this.
There's value in reading Revelation alongside John's own congregations
and thinking with them about how they would have made sense of this word
because it unlocks challenges that Revelation poses to us
that we would tend to miss if we only approach Revelation the way the writers of books that actually sell
approach Revelation, namely as a roadmap for the end times,
whether that be the 19th century, the 20th century, or the 21st century,
they've been bestsellers in every one of those centuries.
Now, I have wrestled with Revelation, and in part, I've been in love with Revelation since I was 13 years old.
I was a strange kid.
I'm a strange adult, let's be honest.
But I first read Revelation when I was 13 years of age, after I'd read through the Gospels and Acts.
Revelation was gripping.
Its fantastic and mysterious images, its cosmic scope, its astounding pronouncements about the stakes involved
in keeping or failing to keep its word.
Revelation was well-crafted to sink its hooks into the reader's mind.
As I sought guidance for understanding this word, and therefore having a chance at keeping this word,
I found that the people with whom I conversed about Revelation tended to have one of two reactions,
with very little in between.
The first is exemplified by the pastor of the Episcopal Church in which I was raised.
He was always open to discussing the faith and the Scriptures with me.
I found him to be a great encouragement throughout those teenage years.
But on this occasion, he admitted he had very little exposure to the book.
So he took me to the church library, sat me down with the last volume in the Old Interpreter's Bible,
and essentially wished me luck.
The second response is exemplified by my maternal grandmother's younger sister,
whom I simply called aunt.
Though raised Baptist, she had joined the Seventh-day Adventist Church.
And she knew exactly what Revelation was about from beginning to end.
She read about it constantly.
And my display of interest, which in retrospect was a bad choice on my part,
but my display of interest to her prompted a steady flow of conversation,
sharing of literature over the space of a decade.
In one setting, Revelation was beyond the purview of the professionals.
In the other setting, it was the interpretive key to the whole Bible,
the focus for study on the part of every active layperson.
In both settings, Revelation was a kind of Pandora's box.
In the first setting, the tendency was to keep a lid on it.
Maybe we'll take a few peeks at the redeemed in the New Jerusalem on All Saints' Day.
But for the most part, the contents of Revelation are kept safely locked away.
In the second setting, every church member becomes a Pandora,
eagerly throwing the box open and allowing its contents to overrun their world.
They chase the beast in this or that political figure.
They follow the whore to this or that country.
They see the gallop of the four horsemen in this or that series of news briefs.
Either way, I believe we lose the witness of John's voice in our churches.
Where Revelation is not read or studied regularly, John simply remains mute.
Where Revelation is avidly consumed as a playbook for the end times,
John's voice in which the interpreters are always inevitably living,
John's voice also goes unheard.
This time, trumped by the interpreters who use Revelation to speak of things about which John never imagined.
In the process, the interpreters and their audiences lose sight of those things
that John did passionately seek to communicate to his churches.
As people get caught up in the imagery of Revelation and try to find answers to these questions,
they often fall headlong into what I would consider be some basic mistakes,
forgetting some of the most basic and important principles of studying the Bible.
In regard to Revelation, I find many popular speakers and writers and the many more who follow them
who have been led astray by three basic fallacies, three myths, if you will, about Revelation.
And this is going to hurt.
Myth number one, Revelation is all about us.
We often forget, in our rush to turn to Scripture, to hear a word for us,
which is a good thing to do, but in our rush to do that,
we forget that all of these texts originally spoke a word for them,
for communities of faith removed from us by at least 19 centuries.
We are the secondary beneficiaries of the pastoral guidance initially intended for them.
John gives us some cues that should serve to remind us as attentive readers
that this book is not in the first instance about us.
Specifically, John signals that Revelation is to be read as a letter.
After the introductory paragraphs, the first three verses,
in which John doesn't speak in his own voice,
but rather in an impersonal voice
that reminds us of the openings of certain books of the Hebrew prophets,
John's own voice sounds out in the fourth verse
in words that recall the opening of other early Christian letters.
John, to the seven churches that are in Asia,
grace to you and peace.
The standard formula with which ancient letters began,
sender to addressees, greetings, is clearly present.
John even uses that modification of the standard greeting
that is already familiar from early Christian letters written by Peter and Paul,
grace to you and peace.
This is a critically important reading cue.
John is writing a letter addressed explicitly to seven real communities of Christians
in the Roman province of Asia, now in western Turkey.
This is reinforced by the divine command that John hears,
write down what you see into a scroll and send it to the seven churches,
to Ephesus and to Smyrna and to Pergamon and to Thyatira and to Sardis
and to Philadelphia and to Laodicea.
This naturally implies that John intended his letter to be understood by them,
to shape their perceptions of their everyday realities,
and to motivate a particular response to their circumstances.
The pervasive use of the number seven in Revelation suggests that the seven churches are in some way
representative of the achievements and the challenges facing churches
across the Mediterranean in the first century and across the globe now,
such that the words addressed to them speak to churches beyond that circle.
Nevertheless, these seven churches are seven real churches facing particular difficulties and situations,
whose response to their world John wanted to affect profoundly.
A grounded and responsible reading of Revelation began disappointing with the second coming of Christ.
All three approaches are based on the assumption that by prophecy,
John primarily indicates that he is communicating predictions about specific events
that will yet unfold at some point in his first audience's future,
and that this is the interpretative key to the book.
They differ only in terms of the time frame of the fulfillment.
What is prophecy?
This, the slides aren't changing on the screens.
Well, that's why there's a handout too.
Anyway, is prophecy essentially prediction?
If Revelation is a prophetic word,
does that mean it is a book of predictions that must be fulfilled at some point in history?
To answer this,
I'm just going to keep advancing my own slides because it makes me feel better.
I would turn to the prophetic utterances of the Hebrew Bible
and to the phenomenon of prophecy within the New Testament
and in early Christian worship.
While such prophecy could include a predictive element,
it was also, and perhaps primarily,
a declaration of God's action in the present
and an announcement of God's evaluation of the present actions of his people,
diagnosing problems, calling for realignment with God's values.
Prophecy is essentially a word from the Lord breaking into the situation of the Lord's people
who need guidance or encouragement or a call to repentance and recommitment.
Prophecy was also a regular experience in the worship life of the Pauline churches.
The new pouring out of God's Holy Spirit on God's people
resulted in the renewed possibility of hearing God's voice
given utterance by the Spirit
through the mouths of those who were possessed by the Spirit.
While there are certainly elements of prediction involved in some prophetic utterances,
such as we can find from Agabus in Acts,
the primary element appears to have been edification,
the revelation of God's perspective
that invited a radical reorientation to one's circumstances,
to one's practices, to one's pursuits.
This certainly emerges from Paul's own understanding
of what prophecy is for
when the prophetic gift is working at its best,
as we read in 1 Corinthians 14.
In John's own situation,
Jezebel, I'm sure that's not her real name, right?
Who names her kid Jezebel?
But Jezebel's own activity as a prophet doesn't involve prediction.
It involves teaching
in regard to the boundaries of acceptable Christian practice,
although in her case,
those boundaries are considerably wider
than John would understand them to be.
In Revelation,
what we typically call the seven letters to the seven churches
are a prime example of,
I would suggest they're better labeled,
the seven oracles to the seven churches,
the seven prophetic words to the seven churches,
because after the command given to John to write down the oracle,
the actual message to each church
begins in a manner that recalls the prophetic formula,
thus says the Lord from the Old Testament.
For example,
these are the words of the Son of God.
The risen and glorified Lord
speaks a word to the churches
through the prophet John,
affirming their strengths,
diagnosing their weaknesses,
calling them to faithful action,
threatening judgment
upon those who are recalcitrant
and promising favor
for those who are penitent and faithful.
In short,
they do precisely what so much
of the prophetic writings of the Old Testament
sought to do for the communities of Israel and Judah.
Where a biblical prophet speaks about the future,
he usually limits the prediction
to the immediately forthcoming future,
not the distant future.
Yet forty days,
and Nineveh will be destroyed.
There will not be dew or rain three years,
but according to my word.
John remains within this range,
seen in his emphasis on the imminence
of the confrontations and events that he merits,
his conviction that he speaks about
what must soon come to pass.
The modern prophecy expert holds that everything presented in the Bible
as a forecast of some future event
must be fulfilled at some point.
If the prophecies of Revelation
do not match historical events or figures
during the first or second century,
they must at some point
have such a match.
This conviction,
this conviction, however,
ignores the primary purpose of prophecy,
which is not to give hard and fast statements
about an unchangeable future,
but to evoke faithful response.
Jonah proclaimed,
Forty days more,
and Nineveh will be destroyed.
In response to this vision of the future
of a larger, invisible world.
And they set the context of the
seven congregations
from a fourth interpretive approach
that has been prominent
in the long history
of interpreting Revelation.
I'm referring now to the idealist approach,
which could also be called
the spiritual reading,
the allegorical reading.
This idealist approach
doesn't read Revelation
primarily as a collection of predictions,
like the historicist,
futurist,
and preterist approaches.
Rather, it approaches Revelation
as a text that uses symbol,
vivid imagery,
and dramatic action
to express transcendent truths
that are valid in every generation.
It essentially reads Revelation
for timeless truth
communicated symbolically
about the cosmic battle
between good and evil
or the trials that must be overcome
by the human soul.
In so doing, however,
the idealist approach
also violates
John's own perspective
on his message
that it is imminent
and therefore a special timeliness
for his congregations,
not timeless.
In this way,
the idealist reading
also overlooks
the close correlation
of Revelation's primary symbols
with the political
and economic realities
that characterized
the Roman province of Asia.
The challenges
of those congregations.
Now's a good chance.
Grab a granola bar.
Perhaps the first
and most obvious thing
they would see
would be many,
many people
who did not share
their convictions
about God
and God's Christ.
An often overlooked challenge
for early Christians
is the bare fact
that the vast majority
of people around them
have little or no place
for the God of Israel
or his crucified Messiah.
They might acknowledge
this God
as a tribal deity
of a particular people
on the fringe
of Rome's empire,
but certainly not
as a deity
as important,
imposing,
or relevant
as the Jews
had historically
made their God
out to be.
If they acknowledged
Jesus at all,
it would probably be
as an executed revolutionary,
a failure at best,
a shameful criminal
at worst.
The lack of confirmation
of the Christian's worldview
in the attitudes
and practices
of their neighbors
who lived,
no doubt,
often happily,
without a care
for the God
of Jesus the Messiah
was undoubtedly
a constant invocation
to question
the correctness
of their own convictions
that enjoyed
so little
social reinforcement.
Another prominent
facet of the life
of these cities,
and indeed
the corollary
of the first,
involved the many
cult sites
of the traditional
Greco-Roman
and local gods
and of the emperors,
the representations
of Roman imperialism.
Ephesus
was famous
throughout the
Mediterranean world
for its temple
of Artemis,
acclaimed one
of the seven wonders
of the ancient world
by frequent travelers,
a source of great
civic pride
and a focus
of civic identity.
The dimensions
of this temple
were staggering,
425 by 225 feet,
four times the footprint
of the Parthenon
in Athens.
Its roof
was supported
by a forest
of 127 columns,
60 feet high.
The story of Paul's
visits to Ephesus
in Acts 19
provides some insight
into the connections
between a famous temple,
the tourist economy,
exemplified by Demetrius
the silversmith
and the production
of silver souvenirs
of Artemis
and civic pride.
And it also shows us
the way in which
the proclamation
of the Christian gospel
intersected
in a hostile manner
with these
at every level.
The Acropolis
of Pergamum
was studded
with prominent
cult sites
of the traditional
Greek gods.
A vast altar
dedicated to Zeus
surrounded by
columned porticos
and all sitting
upon a raised
marble platform
crowned the brow
of the hill
overlooking
the territory below.
Just above it
on the hill
stood a temple
to Athena
which overlooked
a vast theater
carved into
the side
of the hill.
A stage level
of that theater
halfway down
the hill
a temple
to Dionysus
stood in close
proximity
to the theater
whose productions
were often
connected
with the worship
of that God.
On another slope
of the Acropolis
sat a large
temple
sacred
to Demeter
the goddess
of the grain harvest
with a central
altar
and stadium
seating
along one side.
A temple
to Hira
the wife
of Zeus
stood over
the large
gymnasian
complex
on the lower
Acropolis.
Alongside temples
to traditional
gods
stood temples
and other
cult sites
dedicated to
the goddess
Roma
and to the
emperors.
In Pergamon
a temple
was built
to honor
Roma
and Augustus
as early
as 19
BC
with construction
starting a decade
earlier
winning for that
city
the title
of temple
warden
in Greek
neo
coros
of the
imperial
cult.
This coin
minted
under the
emperor
Claudius
shows the
facade
of the
temple
with two
central
pillars
removed
to reveal
the cult
statues
within.
Roma
on the
right
extending
a wreath
of victory
over the
head
of Augustus.
In
Ephesus
the deified
Julius
Caesar
was
worshipped
in a
sacred
enclosure
alongside
Artemis
in the
civic
forum
the
political
district
of the
city.
The
city
also
erected
its own
temple
to
Augustus
and Roma
in the
center
of that
civic
forum.
Toward
the end
of the
first
century
Ephesus
erected
its own
temple
a
magnificent
temple
to honor
Domitian
and his
family
the
Slavian
household
on a
raised
area
overlooking
the
civic
forum.
This
raised
area
was
extended
artificially
with
barrel
vaulted
arches
to support
this
grand
structure
and its
courtyard.
An
ornate
altar
stood
in front
of the
temple
and
colossal
statues
of
Vespasian
Titus
and Domitian
stood
within.
The
remains
of this
cult
image
whether
it's
Titus
or
Domitian
is
disputed
suggests
a
statue
that
once
stood
feet
high.
This
temple
dominated
upper
Ephesus
and
finally
won
that
city
regional
recognition
as an
imperial
temple
warden
male
koros
city
as well.
The
site of
all of
these
temples
remains
an
ever
present
invitation
into
another
story,
the
public
story
about
the
nature
of
Roman
rule.
According
to
John,
this
public
story
that
constantly
surrounds
his
congregations
is
incompatible
with
God's
perspective
on
Roman
rule.
As
this
is a
critical
element
of
Revelation's
word
to
the
churches,
we're
going
to
give
it
more
detailed
attention
in
our
next
session.
For
now,
what's
most
important
to
recognize
is
the
fact
that
early
Christians
were
a
distinctly
minority
report
in the
midst
of a
population
that
oriented
itself
around
the
traditional
Greco-Roman
gods
and that
located
itself
quite
happily
within
the
story
of
Roman
rule.
The
significance
of this
never
impressed
itself
on me
until
I
spent
two
months
in
Sri
Lanka
where
Christians
account
for
only
7%
of
the
population,
a
deeply
religious
population.
Almost
70%
of that
population
would claim
to adhere
to
Buddhism
with
perhaps
15-16%
following
Hinduism.
For
the
converts
or
children
of
converts
to
Christianity
in that
setting,
the
prominence
and the
pervasiveness
of Buddhist
statues
and shrines
and the
visible
signs of
personal
devotion
to
Buddha
that
stretch
from
those
shrines
to the
marketplaces
where people
buy floral
garlands
to honor
statues
of Buddha
in the same
places they
buy their
produce,
their
cell phone
minutes,
and whatever
else.
All of
that
serve as
a constant
reminder to
those Christian
converts
of their
own or
their
family's
departure
from the
worldview
and from
the story
held to
be true
by the
vocal
majority
of their
neighbors.
The
Christian
moving from
his or her
apartments
into the
public spaces
of
Ephesus
would
also
see
everywhere
the
signs
of
trade
and
flourishing
economic
markets.
Pictured
here are
the street
leading to
the harbor
and the
large
commercial
forum
or
agora
of the
lower
city.
The
harbor
at
Ephesus
now
silted
up
after
centuries
of
neglect
was once
a major
port
in the
eastern
Mediterranean
with an
endless
stream
of
merchandise
coming
along
trade
routes
from
the
north
and
from
the
east
to
be
shipped
out
to
ports
closer
to
the
center
of
the
world
above
all
to
Rome
itself.
This
offered
the
urban
Ephesian
and
residents
of
other
major
cities
tied
into
the
network
of
trade
in
the
province
many
opportunities
to
plug
into
the
local
economy
or
the
transportation
industry
thus securing
their own
slice of
the Roman
pie.
Christians
in any
of these
thriving
cities
would see
many
families
living
normal
perhaps
even
better
than
average
lives
and
would
thus
see
much
that
would
be
desirable
for
themselves
and
for
their
own
families.
The
prosperity
promised
by
Rome
and the
possibility
of sharing
in this
prosperity
is a
particularly
important
aspect
of the
situation
of these
congregations.
The lure
of wealth
has sunk
its hooks
quite deep
for example
into the
mouths
of the
Laodicean
Christians
who can
boast of
their own
prosperity
as participants
in their
local economy
while failing
to recognize
their deep
poverty
in Christ's
eyes
as John
Caesar.
No doubt
the hope
for
economic
prosperity
also
provided
the main
motivation
for
developing
a
theology
that
could
accommodate
eating
food
sacrificed
to
idols
something
that
John
identifies
as a
feature
of the
message
of rival
prophets
active
in several
of these
seven
congregations.
...to ask
if we are
to enter
into the
context
and in
private
and to
speak of
their
neighbors
of a
man
whom
a
Roman
prefect
had
Christians
experiencing.
...to ask
a man
whom
a
Roman
prefect
had
Christians
experiencing.
Eastern
Roman
Empire
in some
form
or another.
First,
they
were
participating
in their
city's
life
and
economy.
This
would
require
some
level
of
associate's
religious
practice,
that is,
into some
acknowledgement
of idols
and worship
of the
traditional
gods,
to put a
stumbling
block before
the people
of Israel
so that
they would
eat food
sacrificed
to idols
and practice
fornication.
I have this
against you.
You tolerate
that woman
Jezebel
who calls
herself a
prophet
and is
teaching
and beguiling
my servants
to practice
fornication
and to
eat food
sacrificed
to idols.
...are Jews
and are not
but are a
synagogue
that I have
loved you.
Many feel
pressure from
their neighbors
who do
I also know
that you are
enduring
patiently
and bearing
up for the
sake of my
name.
Neighbors
encounter
exactly and
only the
same pressures
that their
non-Christian
neighbors
encounter
because their
lives are
no different.
The Christians
in Sardis
and Laodicea
seem to pose
a serious
problem for
John
precisely because
they are so
untroubled
by what is
going on
around them
and have
become so
alive
but you
are dead.
I have
not found
your works
complete
in the sight
of my
God.
Yet
you still
have a few
persons in
Sardis
who have
not soiled
their clothes.
I know
your works
not merely
with a
pastoral
letter,
not just
with prophetic
oracles,
not merely
with a
pastoral
letter,
not just
with prophetic
oracles,
but with
an apocalypse,
a text that
we played out
before the
eyes of their
imagination.
We'll be able
to hear you
and we're
recording it.
So if you
could just
come to the
mic and ask
the question,
I'm sure
all the
answers are
here.
I'm sure
all the
answers are
here.
Will those
to whom I
gave five
dollars earlier
to ask
easy questions,
please come
forward.
Revelation as
prediction,
and a
and 18
as
Jerusalem.
...coach tends
to read
Revelation in
terms of the
history of
the oppression
of the church
in the first
three centuries
up to the
legalization of
Christianity
under
Constantine
which
completely
resets the
board for
Christians.
There we go.
We're warming
up.
So for the
different views
that you had
on it,
are these
all exclusive
views,
like if you
hold this
one you
can't hold
these ones,
or are
there some
that combine
in some
ways?
Sure,
good question.
So you
can't be a
preterist
and a
historicist.
You can't
be a
preterist
and a
futurist.
But you
can be a
preterist
and an
idealist.
Or you
can be a
historicist
and an
idealist.
And I
would just
point out
that the
approach that
I'm promoting
is not
any of
the four.
It's
actually
more of
a let's
listen to
revelation
with the
first audiences
and find
out what
sense they
would have
made of it,
how it
would have
challenged and
stretched them.
And on that
basis,
think about how
it challenges
and stretches
us.
Don't have a
cool name for
that yet.
But it
has to
end
an
if,
obviously.
Good morning.
Thanks for
coming.
I've heard
more than
once the
claim challenging
the unique
exclusivity of
Christ.
And I
appreciate that
you bring up
the polytheism
of the day
because I've
heard,
oh,
well,
the Egyptians
had a God
who was born
of a virgin,
died and
rose again,
a son of
God.
Jesus is a
copycat.
Whoa,
hang on.
Right,
the Roman
God,
the Dionysus,
Mithra,
I've heard
of these
before.
They're all
contemporaries
of Jesus.
He copied
their model,
the template
of their
son of
God,
born of
a virgin,
rose from
the dead,
like,
hang on.
Can you
adjust that?
Because there's
an exclusivity
element that's
at stake
where,
where does
the sovereign
Lord really
is sovereign
and exclusive?
compared to
these,
I call
them
subordinate
gods,
right?
So,
it's a
great
question.
So,
and I'm
just answering
off the cuff
here.
The first
thing that
comes to
mind is,
when you
have a
pantheon of
dozens and
dozens of
gods,
you have a
whole bunch
of patterns
and paradigms
that are
available,
that doesn't
mean what
comes later
is a
copycat.
It would
be,
I would
say,
a matter
of unavoidable
coincidence,
and when you
have this
many stories
about this
many gods,
there's going
to be
overlap with
other cultures'
stories about
their many
gods,
and eventually,
monotheistic
religions'
stories about
the one
God.
It's
inevitable
statistically.
The other
thing,
though,
that comes
to mind
is that
the Christian
gospel
doesn't speak
into a
vacuum that
addresses needs
that human
beings have
recognized for
millennia by
that point.
This isn't
exactly hitting
your question,
but that's
typical to
speakers,
right?
They answer
the question
that they're
capable of
answering,
and they
try to make
it look like
they're
actually.
But dying
and rising
gods are
in everybody's
mythology in
the ancient
world.
And I
think that
really says
we mortals
are, and
these dying
and rising
are under
a different
name,
and Dionysus
becomes
in the
first century.
these are
the religions
that people
in the first
century go
to because
the big
temples and
civic
religious
festivals,
they take
care of the
city's
relationship with
the gods,
but they don't
give me hope
of transcending
death.
But if I go
into that
cave and
let the
blood of the
bull
sacrificed to
mithras pour
over me,
I am
initiated into
mithras's
life-giving
power on the
other side of
death, or
whichever mystery
cult.
And all that
says to me
is Christ
provides the
answer to
the crying
need that
people have
exhibited in
these multiple
ways for
centuries before
his coming.
Does that
kind of
satisfy?
Does that
satisfy you
enough for
nine in the
morning?
That's good
enough.
Go for it.
It's okay.
Maybe you
should just
stay up here.
I have to
teach public
speaking this
fall to some
students, so
maybe this is
practice.
Now, there's
an element of
mystery that
remains that
may be
appropriate, but
I don't have
it quite
articulated
perfectly in
maybe nobody
does or
should, but
thank you.
I didn't have
the words for
it.
I kind of
knew, I
couldn't
articulate it,
so I
needed, yeah,
you covered
it without
tying a
perfect bow
on it, but
yeah, it's
fine.
It wants
me, it
encourages me
to study
more, like
dig deeper
into the
Greco-Roman
space, because
that's not
what I
study normally.
Decent
answer,
three and a
half stars.
Thank you.
So, the
verse is
right here
in front
of us, and
I was
intrigued when
I was reading
your book
about how
we interpret
being either
cold, being
hot, and I
just wanted to
could elaborate
on that, because
for me, it
was just so
eye-opening.
thank you for
that softball
pitch.
So, it's
very common
to hear that
bottom verse
preached this
way.
Jesus would
prefer that
the people
not be
Christians at
all, or be
fervent
Christians, rather
than to be,
well, you know,
like most of
you.
No, just
kidding, just
kidding.
But that's
completely wrong,
because cold
and hot are
both good
things, right?
But Jesus
would never
prefer that
you be
totally just
alienated from
the faith
or fervent.
And think
about water
in these
cities.
Cold water
is refreshing
and good.
Hot water
is relaxing
and therapeutic.
All of
these cities
had baths
with saunas
and hot
tubs
and cold
plunges, and
it was just
part of the
culture.
At
banquets,
you could
be served
drinks that
had been
chilled,
because this
is how good
the economy
was.
Snow could
be transported
from the
top of
mountains
and sold
in the
marketplace
to people
who were
rich enough
to delight
their guests
with chilled
beverages.
And wine
could be
served hot
and spiced.
You know,
grue-wein
is not just
a modern
German phenomenon.
So,
the problem,
of course,
is that
lukewarm
water,
water slightly
heated,
was in fact
served at
banquets to
help you
vomit.
Well,
you know,
just to make
room for the
next course.
If you've
ever gone
to Helen
and Chris's
house for
a banquet,
you know
you need
to make
room for
the next
course.
So,
that's
really more
the background.
And the
hot and the
cold don't
need to be
interpreted
in this.
Jesus goes
right on to
say what's
wrong with
the churches.
What makes
them lukewarm
is the fact
that they are
thinking about
themselves and
about,
they're gauging
their own
well-being on
exactly the
terms of the
society around
them and
not in
terms of
the way
Christ is
looking at
them and
their witness.
They're thinking
that there's
nothing wrong
with being
immersed in
this exploitative
economy for
their own
benefit.
So,
Jesus has
to wake
them up to
their real
spiritual
temperature so
as to shock
them into
rethinking,
wait a minute,
can you
talk a
little bit
about the
history of
this method
of interpreting
the Scriptures
because I
think we
hear this,
especially in
our stream of
the church,
this letter
wasn't written
to you,
enter the
context of
the people
that it was
written to,
but then we
also have a
bunch of
interpretations
in historic
Christianity that
didn't take that
approach and so
I'm curious,
kind of how
we got here
if this was
something that
existed like
as distance
grew from the
original recipient
to the letter.
Excellent.
So,
just to be a
little glib,
this is an
ancient approach
because this is
exactly how
those first
Christians read
it.
But,
as your
question already
intimates,
by the time we
get to the
late second
century,
people like
Irenaeus are
reading Revelation
quite differently.
They have
left the
context of
those first
century Christians
behind and
he's reading it
expecting something
in the third
century to
happen.
And,
just frankly,
that becomes
a way of
things.
Christian
teachers in
every century
demonstrable from
that point on
are reading
Revelation as
prediction
or as a
way to put
labels on
their immediate
enemies.
That's the
other favorite
way.
And in
every century
for which we
actually have
evidence,
7th and 8th and
9th century,
they're called the
Dark Ages for a
reason.
Not a lot has
survived from
those centuries.
But it's also
very common to
use this book
to call
someone the
beast or
Babylon.
So, we do
actually have
some 7th and
8th century
readings and
not surprisingly,
that's the time
of the Arab
conquest.
So,
suddenly,
Revelation is
all about the
Arab conquest
and the
Muslim
influx into
North Africa
and the
Middle East
and eventually
into
Constantinople.
Of course,
the Reformation,
right?
Revelation
becomes a
great tool
to talk
about the
Pope,
to badmouse
the Pope.
And it
continues to
this day.
I would say
thinking about
Revelation with
its first
years is
really,
really starts
to be recovered
in the
18th century
where,
again,
the New
Testament
scholars
began to
think,
what if you
read Revelation
the way
we read
Galatians?
What if
we dispense
with a
name-calling
and just
try to
understand
Revelation?
And there
is an
assumption.
The assumption
is that
Revelation would
have been
intelligible to
the people
John actually
cared about.
I happen to
think that's a
very safe
assumption.
but there
it is.
So, yeah,
about three
centuries.
It doesn't
begin to
sell as
well as
the other.
I'll stick
on that
stream,
Dr.
David.
But the
idea that
it's my
mic one.
Yeah, my
mic's on.
You don't
need a mic
for me,
but for the
people online.
So, it's a
fair assessment
to say that
John's book
of Revelation
is more
concerned
with
faithful
witness of
the churches
that he is
pastoring
than
predicting
the future.
I want to
make sure
we all
heard that
and we're
all tracking
with that
idea that
this is
political
witness to
Christ
versus and
above the
environments and
cultural environments
that they
kind of
themselves.
So, I
don't want to
entirely go
that route
because Revelation
clearly overlaps
with other New
Testament teaching
about what's
going to
happen.
Point is,
every verse
of Revelation
is about
something that's
going to
happen.
we still
read in
Revelation
about what
it means to
live in the
expectation of
Christ's coming.
In the
expectation that
whatever nation
we're living in
the world,
it's not the
be-all and
end-all of
human history,
but it's just
one more
kingdom of
this world that
will either
fade away or
will yield to
the kingdom of
God and
his Messiah.
These are
convictions shared
across the
writings in the
New Testament.
However,
the favorite
passages for
prophecy experts
are Revelation
12 and
13 and
Revelation 17
and 18.
And we're
going to look
in our next
session,
thank you for the
segue, Corey,
about the ways in
which those four
chapters make
immediate sense to
people in the
first century.
and so are
probably not
part and
parcel of
the future
that John
is looking at,
but rather the
lifting of a
veil from
things that are
very present
and real from
those early
Christians so
that they see
them not as
their neighbors
see them anymore,
but as God
sees them.
And seeing
them in that
different light
suddenly makes
them orient
themselves toward
the world
that they live
in very
differently.
And that, I
think, is the
ongoing power of
Revelation.
I'll just close
our first session
with this.
We live in
very troubled
political and
economic times,
and it's
difficult to
navigate faithful
discipleship in
the midst of
the strong
currents that
are rippling
through our
society.
Revelation has
a lot to
help us
listen past
the propaganda
from every
side and
hear God's
word to
show us the
ways forward
that doesn't
leave us
seduced and
harnessed by
any temporal
agenda.
I'll just
put it that
way.
So, we
have a break
of how
long?
Ten-minute
break, come
back.
So, session
two.
Or don't.
I get paid the
same either way.
Just kidding.
I get paid the
money.
Thank you.
John draws a very different picture.
And the society and the structures in which the members of these seven congregations live.
And it's the story that John most directly challenges in his revelation of the way things really are in the sight of the one God.
And the second part.
And the story of the Augustan age.
And the story of the world.
would be to bring the family would be to bring the world.
And the future of the sun and the sun.
And we're not under.
And the one world.
And it's seen as the world.
And the first of the world.
Everlasting.
from the world.
And the trees there.
And the other.
And the same.
And the truth.
And the other.
in the sense that the world.
Augustus.
And the early empire.
This list was inscribed.
far from being a.
And the first.
And the other.
in a prominent.
what we would call.
calendar year.
Caesar.
The word from the word.
whose gifts.
son of a God.
Augustus.
And the other.
in the first.
gifts.
of Roma.
under under.
As we've seen.
in life.
in Roma.
and the people.
of the people.
the Pergamos.
and the people.
stone.
on these.
And the people.
and who are proclaiming.
and the people.
wine or incense.
as in the name.
It's very typical.
to the year.
and the world.
and the people.
the air would be filled.
participating.
to do one.
and the people.
water into blood.
what it means.
and the people.
and the ideologies.
and the images.
and the people.
John accuses.
came to the people.
and the people.
John's vision.